Otto Klemperer Archive
Music Division, Library of Congress
Guides to Special Collections in the Music Division of the Library of Congress
Otto Klemperer Archive 1792-1988 (bulk 1920-circa 1970)
ML31.K59
Klemperer, Otto, 1885-1973
20,000 items 111 containers 29 linear feet
Music Division Library of Congress Washington, D.C.
Conductor and composer. The archive documents Otto Klemperer's life and career. It contains manuscript and printed music, correspondence, family papers, writings by and about Klemperer, interviews, legal and financial documents, clippings, programs, photographic materials, materials related to the Kroll Opera, and books annotated by Klemperer and his daughter Lotte. The archive also contains production and resource materials, including scripts, interviews, background materials, and photographs, that Philo Bregstein used in making a documentary film about Klemperer's life and work.
Selected Search Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the Library's online catalog. They are grouped by name of person or organization, by subject or location, and by occupation and listed alphabetically therein.
People
Bregstein, Philo, 1932-; Klemperer, Lotte.; Klemperer, Otto, 1885-1973--Archives.; Klemperer, Otto, 1885-1973--Correspondence.; Klemperer, Otto, 1885-1973--Interviews.; Klemperer, Otto, 1885-1973--Manuscripts.; Klemperer, Otto, 1885-1973--Photographs.; Klemperer, Otto, 1885-1973.; Klemperer, Otto, 1885-1973.; Klemperer, Otto, 1885-1973. Selections.
Organizations
Krolloper.; Los Angeles Philharmonic Orchestra.
Subjects
Conductors (Music)--Interviews.; Music--Manuscripts.
Form/Genre
Clippings (Information artifacts); Correspondence.; Financial records.; Photographic prints.; Programs (Documents)
Administrative Information
Provenance
Gift; from daughter Lotte Klemperer; 1980-1989 and 2003.
Accruals
No further accruals are expected.
Transfers
The sound recordings, video recordings, and films were transferred to the Motion Picture, Broadcasting and Recorded Sound Division in the Library of Congress.
A portion of the music-related printed books were cataloged separately and shelved in the general collections of the Library of Congress, Music Division.
A portion of the non-music printed books were transferred to the Anglo-American Acquisition Division, Exchange Program, Library of Congress.
Other Repositories
Additional materials pertaining to Otto Klemperer may be available at the following institutions: California State University, Music Library, Los Angeles, California; Juilliard School, Lila Acheson Wallace Library, Lonny Epstein Collection, New York; Leo Baeck Institute, New York; Hebrew University, Jerusalem; Gustav Mahler Archiv, Archiv Eleonore Vondenhoff, Frankfurt; Zentralbibliothek, Zurich; Deutsches Literaturarchive, Kroll Archiv, Hans Curjel; Santa Monica College, Music Dept., Santa Monica, California; and Royal Academy of Music, London.
Related Material
Additional materials pertaining to Otto Klemperer may be found in the
Moldenhauer Archive, Music Division, Library of Congress.
The Library of Congress Music Division also contains a small collection of correspondence to and from Otto Klemperer shelved separately under ML94.K55.
Access and Restrictions
The materials in the Otto Klemperer Archive are open to research. Researchers are advised to contact the Music Division prior to visiting in order to determine whether the desired materials will be available at that time.
Certain restrictions to use or copying of materials may apply.
Biographical Note
Date Event
1885, May 14 Born, Breslau, Germany, to Nathan and Ida Rée Klemperer
1889 Moved to Hamburg with father, mother, older sister Regina (Regi), and younger sister Marianne
1891 Began piano lessons with Havekoss after having been taught by mother
1901 Moved to Frankfurt to study piano with Dutch pianist James Kwast; theory with Ivan Knorr; and violin at the Hoch Conservatory, Frankfurt am Main
1902 Continued piano studies with Kwast and theory with Philipp Schwarwenka at the Klindworth-Scharwenka Conservatory, Berlin
1905 Followed Kwast to the Stern Conservatory, Berlin to continue piano studies
Began conducting and composition studies under Hans Pfitzner
Conducted the off-stage orchestra for Mahler’s Symphony no. 2
Met Gustav Mahler for first time during rehearsal
1906 Engaged as chorus master and deputy director for Max Reinhardt’s production of Offenbach’s Orpheus in the Underworld at the Neues Theater, Berlin
Berlin debut as conductor after second performance
1907-1910 Chorus master and assistant conductor, Deutsches Landestheater, Prague (upon recommendation of Gustav Mahler)
Conducting debut with von Weber’s Der Freischütz
1910-1912 Assistant conductor, Hamburg Stadttheater
Conducting debut with Wagner’s Lohengrin
1911 Entered clinic at Königstein to treat depression
Diagnosed as manic-depressive
1912 Conducted Der Ring des Nibelungen for first time
1913-1914 Became first conductor of opera at Barmen
Conducting debut with Wagner’s Tannhäuser
1914-1917 Deputy musical director under Hans Pfitzner, Strasbourg Stadttheater
Opened with revival of Beethoven’s Fidelio
1915-1917 During manic periods, composed numerous compositions
Conducted farewell concert in Strasbourg which included some of own works
1917-1924 Musical director of Cologne Opera
Debuted with Mozart’s Figaro
1919 Received instruction from a Jesuit priest, and subsequently converted to Catholicism
In spring, began composing a mass
In June, married soprano Johanna Geissler
1920 Son Werner born
1920-1921 Conducted in Vienna and Barcelona
Conducted Berlin Philharmonic Orchestra in Schoenberg’s Verklärte Nacht and Pelleas und Melisande, and Mahler’s Symphony No. 2
1923 Rejected directorship of Deutsches Opernhaus, Berlin
Mother Ida Klemperer died
First public performance of his Mass in C
In November, daughter Lotte born
1924 Father Nathan Klemperer died and buried in Cologne’s Jewish cemetery alongside his wife
1924-1927 Musical director, Wiesbaden Opera (almost every opera performance was a new production or revival)
Debuted with Beethoven’s Fidelio
Conducted several concerts with Berlin Philharmonic Orchestra
1924-1936 Conducted in Russia
Debuted in Moscow and Leningrad
1926-1927 Conducted New York Symphony Orchestra
Gave first American performance of Hindemith's Concert Music for Wind Orchestra, op. 41
1927-1931 Director, Berlin State Opera
General musical director, Staatsoper am Platz der Republik (known as the Kroll Opera)
Directed works by Stravinsky, Hindemith, Krenek, and Schoenberg
Conducted no fewer than ten symphony orchestra concerts each year with Berlin Staatskapelle
1928-1929 Conducted orchestras in Hamburg, Breslau, Rome, and, for first time, in Paris
Conducting debut in London with Bruckner’s Symphony no. 8
Composed an Ave Maria and a Pater Noster
1931, July 3 Last performance of Kroll Opera in Berlin
Klemperer given leave of absence after filing legal suit over closure of Kroll
Spent May-October conducting at Theatro Colón, Buenos Aires
1931-1933 Musical director, Berlin Staatsoper Unter der Linden
New production of Mozart’s Così Fan Tutte
Conducted Staatskapelle Orchestra
1933 Feb. Suffered concussion during accident at Gewandhaus Orchestra rehearsal, Leipzig; unable to conduct performance
1933 Apr. Left Germany for Zurich (partly due to effect of political situation on conducting in Berlin and partly to get treatment for manic-depression)
Joined by wife and children
1933 May-1935 Mar. Established residence in Vienna
Conducted Los Angeles Philharmonic, New York Philharmonic, and Philadelphia Symphony Orchestra as well as orchestras in Vienna, Warsaw, Budapest, Rome, and Milan
1935 Apr.-June Returned to California and took out naturalization papers for American citizenship
In June, joined by wife and children
1935 Oct.-1936 Mar. Conducted series of concerts with New York Philharmonic, including performance of Mahler’s Symphony no. 2, (The Resurrection)
Not offered conductor positions with Philadelphia Symphony Orchestra or New York Philharmonic
1936-1939 In fall 1936, resumed conducting position with Los Angeles Philharmonic Orchestra
Made guest conducting appearances elsewhere in United States, various European cities, and in Russia
1939 Sept. Diagnosed with nerve tumor on right side of head which affected hearing and balance
Had operations which caused partial paralysis of right side of face and body
Had additional surgery which caused partial atrophy of tongue resulting in indistinct speaking
1940 Sept. Took oath of allegiance to become U. S. citizen
1940 Sept.-Nov. Dismissed as conductor of Los Angeles Philharmonic; publicly called "retirement" by the orchestra association
Conducted series of concerts in New York City
1941 Feb.-Apr. Public episodes of manic-depression increased, damaging reputation; guest conducting appearances were few over next several years
1946 Conducted concerts in Europe including Baden-Baden where he was first great émigré musician to return to his native country
1947-1948 Conducted Budapest Opera, including a cycle of Mozart operas, several Wagner operas, and numerous orchestra concerts
1948-1950 Continued conducting at Budapest Opera as well as numerous orchestras in Europe and two conducting tours in Australia
Audience with Pope Pius XII in Rome
1951 Mar.-Aug. Conducted recording project with Vienna Philharmonic Orchestra
Toured South America including conducting engagements in Argentina and Venezuela
1951 Oct. Fell and fractured femur in left leg in Montreal
Unable to conduct until spring of 1952
1952 Signed recording contract with EMI (jeopardized by American Federation of Musicians preventing members from conducting foreign-staffed orchestras)
1952 Nov. Request for passport extension unanswered, suspected of subversive activities on behalf of both Nazi regime and Communist International
In Montreal, Klemperer and family ordered to return to United States by December 23, 1952, or lose their American citizenship
1952 Dec. Family moved to New York City
1953 Conducted a few concerts in Chicago, Pittsburgh, Montreal
Departed for European conducting tour with passports stamped not to be extended, assuring that on return they would resume residency in United States
1954 May Klemperer, wife, and daughter decided not to return to United States
Obtained German passports after establishing German residency
Family moved to Zurich (son remained in United States to continue acting career)
1954 July Lotte became father's traveling companion and assumed total responsibility for conducting engagements, recording contracts, fees, and selections of artists and orchestras
1954-1955 Conducted concerts and made recordings with London’s Philharmonia Orchestra
Became their principal conductor
1956 Nov. Wife Johanna died
“Bist Du bei mir” and “Wenn ich einmal muss scheiden” by Bach played at funeral in Munich
1958, April 8 Received highest decoration, Grosses Verdienstkreuz mit Stern, from German Federal Republic at West German embassy in London
1958 Sept. Suffered second- and third-degree burns over 15% of his body while conducting in London
1959 Aug. Appointed “principal conductor for life” of the Philharmonia Orchestra and resumed conducting despite continuing health problems
1961 Feb. Conducted Beethoven’s Fidelio at Covent Garden
Continued composing and hired Philharmonia for private concert of his music
1962 Jan.-May Conducted new production of Mozart’s Die Zauberflöte at Covent Garden
Conducted first public performance of his Symphony no. 1 (Symphony in Two Movements)
1963 In April, conducted new production of Wagner’s Lohengrin at Covent Garden
Conducted Mahler’s Symphony no. 2 with Vienna Philharmonic
1964 March Philharmonia Orchestra suspended operations leaving Klemperer without an orchestra
Orchestra players elected governing body to run Philharmonia themselves with Klemperer as president and ten dates to conduct in 1964-65 season
1964-1965 Conducted London’s New Philharmonia Orchestra for fee to raise funds for newly formed orchestra
In early April, elder sister Regi Elbogen died in Holland
1967 Jan. Klemperer resolved to leave Roman Catholic Church and return to his Jewish faith
1967 Sept. Invested with Germany’s highest honor, the Pour le Mérite, at West German embassy in Berne
1968 March Conducted several of his own compositions, including Symphony no. 2, with New Philharmonia Orchestra before small audience of friends
1968 May On his last visit to Vienna, conducted Vienna Philharmonic Orchestra, his favorite orchestra, in series of five concerts
1969 Conducted revival of Beethoven’s Fidelio at Covent Garden
1969 May Conducted three concerts in Paris with Orchestre de Paris where he celebrated eighty-fourth birthday
1969 Sept. Conducted first public performance of his Symphony no. 2
1970 Jan. Recording of Mozart’s Le Nozze di Figaro won coveted Deutsche Schallplatten prize
1970 late May Conducted last Beethoven cycle with New Philharmonia Orchestra; filmed for television by BBC
1970 Sept. Conducted two concerts with New Philharmonia Orchestra in Bonn, Germany, for bicentenary celebration of Beethoven’s birth; last time conducting in Germany and last time conducting Beethoven symphony
1972 Jan. Due to ill health, prevented from conducting Bruckner’s Symphony no. 7 in London
Decided to conduct only in recording studio
1972 July Klemperer visited Lotte Lehman in Lucerne; became seriously ill with pneumonia and would never fully regain strength
1972 Dec. Withdrew from EMI recording project because of ill health (Klemperer never worked again)
Daughter requested that Klemperer’s name as chief conductor be removed from all New Philharmonia literature
1973 English language version of 1968 German documentary film Otto Klemperer’s Journey through His Times is released (produced by Dutch film director Philo Bregstein)
1973 April New Philharmonia performed Klemperer’s Symphony no. 2 under Lorin Maazel; Klemperer not strong enough to attend; received copy of program signed by all participants
1973, May 14 Celebrates eighty-eighth birthday with few old friends
1973 July 6 Died after slipping into coma at end of June in Zurich, Switzerland
Buried four days later in Jewish cemetery at Friesenberg, Switzerland with plain Jewish rite
Scope and Content Note
Otto Klemperer is known primarily for his artistry as a conductor, particularly of contemporary music and operas during the 1920s and 1930s, and of orchestral music by Beethoven, Bruckner, Mozart, and Mahler. He is less well-known for his compositions, which include symphonies, string quartets, songs, piano solos, choral works, an opera, and arrangements.
The "Music" series includes holograph scores or sketches of most of Klemperer's published and unpublished compositions, as well as copyists' and printed instrumental parts or scores, some with his emendations or annotations. The collection also includes the German texts for many poems written by Goethe, Heine, and others that Klemperer set to music. In addition, his arrangements of works by Bach, Mendelssohn, Mozart and others are represented by holograph, copyists' and printed scores. This series also contains music manuscripts and copyists' scores written by Klemperer's parents, his wife, and other composers. In addition, there is a selection of printed music scores from the eighteenth through the twentieth centuries. Many items contain Klemperer's notations.
The "Family Papers" series consists of genealogies with family trees, letters, news clippings and other information about Otto Klemperer’s ancestors from the nineteenth century. It also contains information on more recent Klemperer family members.
The "Correspondence" series contains a small amount of letters regarding specific pieces of music, transactions with publishing companies, and donations of Klemperer materials to various educational institutions.
The "Writings" series includes lectures and speeches by Klemperer; articles and anecdotes about him; and interviews he gave from 1914 to 1981. Klemperer wrote about musicians and composers, including Bartók, Berg, Bruckner, Hindemith, Mahler, Schoenberg, Shostakovich, Sibelius, Stravinsky, Wagner, and Zemlinsky, many whose works he conducted throughout his career. In addition, he wrote about the Vienna Philharmonic, the Berlin Philharmonic Choir, the conductor Toscanini, the Kroll Opera, and topics such as conducting by memory as opposed to with a score, contemporary music, and working for art’s sake, among other subjects. The materials written about Klemperer include anecdotes and articles in various languages, translations of Russian articles, and transcripts of broadcasts and film scripts. The interviews with Klemperer were used in European and Canadian radio broadcasts and in the film made of his life by Philo Bregstein.
The "Legal and Financial Papers" series contains inquiries made through the Freedom of Information Act about U. S. government surveillance of Klemperer during the years after World War II. It also contains his and family members' citizenship certificates and passports, income tax returns, insurance policies, and correspondence with lawyers.
The "Kroll Opera" series deals with Klemperer's leadership of the Staatsoper am Platz der Republik in Berlin, also known as the Kroll Oper. His tenure there, from 1927 to 1931, marks a controversial period in his career. At the same time, it solidified his reputation as a conductor and musical director. This series contains original and photocopied newspaper clippings, articles, and reviews of Kroll Opera productions, of concerts Klemperer conducted with the Berlin Staatsoper Kapelle Orchester, and commentaries on specific works that were performed at the opera house. In addition, there are black and white photographs of the interior and exterior of the Kroll Opera and black and white and color photographic reproductions of set designs for productions such as Fidelio, Die Zauberflöte, Stravinsky’s Oedipus Rex and Petrouska, Wagner’s Der fliegende Holländer, among others. The series also includes programs from different opera productions and orchestra concerts; radio transcripts from Südwest Radio and West German Radio, spanning 1961-1962; a doctoral dissertation on the Berlin State Opera from 1918-1931 by John Sargent Rockwell; and numerous reviews of works Klemperer performed at the Kroll, including Hindemith’s Cardillac, Fidelio, Oedipus Rex, Strauss’ Der Rosenkavalier, Schoenberg’s Erwartung, and Bach’s St. Matthew Passion, among others.
The "Clippings" series includes photocopies of news clippings, press releases, articles, and typescripts about Klemperer’s various conducting engagements, mostly in the United States. They date from 1926 to 1972.
The "Programs" series contains original programs as well as photocopies and typescripts of programs for various Klemperer concerts. The programs cover different orchestras which Klemperer conducted, including the Los Angeles Philharmonic Orchestra from 1933 to 1939.
The "Iconography" series includes an assortment of black and white photographs from different time periods of Klemperer's life and four photograph albums, two of which consist of black and white photographs of Klemperer alone or conducting, from 1919 to 1969; and two albums that contain black and white photographs of Klemperer conducting in London from 1970 to 1971. An additional album contains original watercolors of set designs for the Wiesbaden Opera.
The "Miscellaneous Printed Matter" series includes a variety of articles, books, programs, an opera libretto, and photocopies of encyclopedia entries. In addition, it contains an article on Gustav Mahler by Max Brod; Erwin Jacobi’s article on Albert Schweitzer and Richard Wagner; several items by Albert Schweitzer; and Lipman-Wulf’s article on his sculpture Otto Klemperer Conducting.
In 1968, Philo Bregstein made a German-language documentary film on Klemperer’s life and work. Klemperer is interviewed in the film, and at times portions of the interview are used as narration. The background materials used for making this film are part of the "Klemperer Film Materials" series. This series also contains the typewritten film script with emendations; photocopies and typescripts of statements by and about Klemperer; and interviews with Klemperer by Bregstein and Klemperer's biographer, Peter Heyworth. The interviews with Klemperer include discussions about Ernst Bloch, Pierre Boulez, Hans Curjel, Paul Dessau, Klemperer's children Werner and Lotte, Rafael Kubelik, Lotte Lehman, Helmuth Plessner, and H. H. Stuckenschmidt, among others.
This series also contains an extensive amount of production materials for the film. Included are photographic prints, contact prints, slides, and negatives, some original and some reproduced from various European archives, all very loosely organized. These materials pertain to various subjects, including Otto Klemperer, depictions of the Weimar Republic, Germany during the Nazi period, World War II and the effects of the war, German cultural life from the turn of the century to the post World War II period, various artists, and European and American cities where Klemperer lived and worked. Index cards identify the subject matter of the photoprints.
The "Books" series contains 109 books from Klemperer's collection. Books were retained if they had annotations by Otto Klemperer and his daughter Lotte or if material was laid into the book. Biographies of Otto Klemperer and books which contain references to him include annotations by Lotte Klemperer and errata sheets clarifying inaccuracies in the text. The original laid-in material and photocopies of the annotated pages from the books have been filed separately along with a complete list of books. Books annotated by Otto Klemperer include Mozart: sein Charakter sein Werk by Einstein, Goethes Briefe an Frau von Stein bu Goethe, Hundejahre by Gunter Grass, Max Henning’s translation of Der Koran, Ethik by Spinoza, Vom Ewigen im Menschen by Scheler, Rösch’s translation of Das neue Testament, Die Unschuld des Werdens by Nietzsche; der Nachlass, and Mayer’s translation of Der babylonische Talmud. In addition, there are books inscribed and signed by Anna Freud, Ernst Bloch, Igor Stravinsky, Helmuth Plessner, and Robert Craft.
A bronze bust of Otto Klemperer was donated to the Library of Congress by the sculptress Anna Mahler Joseph and now resides in the Whittall Pavilion in the Thomas Jefferson Building.
The Appendix at the end of the finding aid includes an index linking the original folder numbers created by Lotte Klemperer to the present box and folder locations of the material in the Otto Klemperer Archive.
William Nelson, Technician
Wilda Heiss, Music Specialist
Organization of the Otto Klemperer Archive
The Otto Klemperer Archive is organized into twelve series:
Music, 1915-1971
Family Papers, 1792-1983
Correspondence, 1915-1974
Writings, 1914-1981
Legal and Financial Papers, 1934-1984
Kroll Opera, 1918-1965
Clippings, 1926-1972
Programs, 1901-1967
Iconography, 1924-1971
Miscellaneous Printed Matter, 1930-1977
Klemperer Film Materials, 1885-1972
Books, 1901-1988
http://lccn.loc.gov/2006560666
Container List
- Music, 1915-1971 (Box 1-43, 103-106, 108)
  - Works by Otto Klemperer (Box 1-37, 103-106, 108)
    Includes holograph and copyists' manuscripts; full scores and parts, some with emendations and annotations; photocopies; transparencies; and printed music.
    Arranged alphabetically by title.
    - Abschied von Paris, Holograph manuscript full score; On t.p.: Ade Paris!; On p. 1 and at end: 23.11.67 Zürich. (Box-folder 1/1)
    - Abschied von Paris, Copyist's manuscript full score; On t.p.: 1967. (Box-folder 1/2)
    - Adagio, Photocopy of holograph manuscript for piano (Box-folder 1/3)
    - Adagio, Photocopy of copyist's manuscript for piano (Box-folder 1/3)